A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Population Program, Office Files of Tim Rice FA678
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Population Program, Office Files of Tim Rice
1957-1982
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA678
16.8 Cubic Feet
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Conditions Governing Access note
Material is open for scholarly research, with prior archival review.
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment. Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Ford Foundation
- Regional Files, 1960-1982; I
  - Latin America -- General -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Brazil -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1969-1980 (Box 1)
  - Caribbean -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Caribbean -- Jamaica -- General, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Chile -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Colombia -- General, 1969-1979 (Box 1)
  - Colombia -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1967-1976 (Box 1)
  - Colombia -- FEPAFEM, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Colombia -- ASCOFAME, 1965-1969 (Box 1)
  - Conferences -- Latin America -- Caracas Meeting on Population Policies in Relation to Development in Latin America and Memoranda from Robert Wickham Re: Population Activities in Latin America, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Conferences -- Latin America -- Pan-American Conference on the Teaching of Demography in Medical Schools (Bogota), Jun 1968 (Box 1)
  - Conferences -- Latin America and the Caribbean -- Social Sciences and Population (Mexico City), Jun 9-13, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Mexico -- General, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Peru -- General, 1965-1971 (Box 1)
  - Peru -- Ford Foundation Activities (1/2), 1967-1980 (Box 1)
  - Peru -- Ford Foundation Activities (2/2), 1967-1980 (Box 1)
  - Venezuela -- General, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Venezuela -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1967-1974 (Box 1)
  - Middle East and Africa -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Africa -- General -- Conferences, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Egypt -- Arab Republic of Egypt (ARE) -- General and Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Egypt (A.R.E.) -- Narratives, 1967 (Box 1)
  - French Language Resource Base, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Ghana -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Nigeria -- General, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Nigeria -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1970-1977 (Box 2)
  - Tunisia -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1965-1970 (Box 2)
  - Uganda -- Visit -- Saunders and Radel, Mar 1969 (Box 2)
  - Zambia -- Reports, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- General Family Planning and Population Papers -- Memoranda, Reports, Conference Materials, 1970-1974 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- General, 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- General -- Papers, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- General, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- General, 1970-1976 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- East Pakistan -- General, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- Monthly Report -- Population Council, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
  - Pakistan -- Population Advisor Search, 1970 (Box 2)
  - "Population, Planning and the Metamorphic Transformation of Pakistan" by Quentin W. Lindsey, Dec 1970 (Box 2)
  - South and Southeast Asia -- Overseas Division Reports, 1968-1973 (Box 2)
  - South and Southeast Asia -- General, 1968-1972 (Box 2)
  - Asia -- Ford Foundation Activities -- "A Review of the Foundation's Work in Asia" by Ozzie Simmons and Samuel Bunker, Jun 1973 (Box 2)
  - Asia -- Social Sciences -- Memoranda and Reports, 1968-1973 (Box 2)
  - Bangladesh -- Ford Foundation Activities -- Reports (1/2), 1973-1976 (Box 2)
  - Bangladesh -- Ford Foundation Activities -- Reports (2/2), 1973-1976 (Box 2)
  - International Center for Diarrhoeal Research, Bangladesh -- Reports, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Dacca, Bangladesh Field Office Publications, 1974-1977 (Box 3)
  - Ceylon -- General, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
  - Ceylon -- Population Council/Ford Foundation Monthly Reports, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - China (mainland) -- Pre-1973, 1970 (Box 3)
  - China (mainland), 1974-1977 (Box 3)
  - Hong Kong -- General, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - India -- Family Planning -- Various Reports, 1967-1970 (Box 3)
  - India -- Population and Family Planning -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports (1/4), 1969-1976 (Box 3)
  - India -- Population and Family Planning -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports (2/4), 1969-1976 (Box 3)
  - India -- Population and Family Planning -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports (3/4), 1969-1976 (Box 3)
  - India -- Population and Family Planning -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports (4/4), 1969-1976 (Box 3)
  - India -- Ford Foundation -- Family Planning Program (general), 1967-1976 (Box 3)
  - India -- "Fertility in Family Planning Schedules for Use in the 1971 India Census" Memorandum by Lyle Saunders, Jul 30, 1969 (Box 3)
  - India -- "Incentives in the Ecology and Adoption of Family Planning in Rural India" by Edward M. Humberger, Dec 11, 1969 (Box 3)
  - India -- "Health and Nutrition in India - Recommendations for Ford Foundation Support" by Davidson R. Gwatkin (1/2, 2 copies), Jan 1974 (Box 3)
  - India -- "Health and Nutrition in India - Recommendations for Ford Foundation Support" by Davidson R. Gwatkin (2/2, 2 copies), Jan 1974 (Box 3)
  - India -- Ford Foundation -- Condoms -- Consultants on Manufacturing and Studies Re: Other Forms of Contraception, 1967 (Box 3)
  - India -- Demography -- Vital Registration, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - India -- Population -- Excerpts from Agenda Papers of the Fourth Meeting, Central Family Planning Council of India, Oct 6-7, 1967 (Box 3)
  - India -- Vasectomy Camps -- Report, "The Ernakulam Camps", Sep 1971 (Box 3)
  - India -- Newspaper Clippings, 1965-1976 (Box 3)
  - India -- Ford Foundation, "Program Letter - Family Planning" Issues, 1969-1972 (Box 4)
  - India -- Staff and Consultants Papers Re: Population and Family Planning (1/7), 1963-1974 (Box 4)
  - India -- Staff and Consultants Papers Re: Population and Family Planning (2/7), 1963-1974 (Box 4)
  - India -- Staff and Consultants Papers Re: Population and Family Planning (3/7), 1963-1974 (Box 4)
  - India -- Staff and Consultants Papers Re: Population and Family Planning (4/7), 1963-1974 (Box 4)
  - India -- Staff and Consultants Papers Re: Population and Family Planning (5/7), 1963-1974 (Box 4)
  - India -- Staff and Consultants Papers Re: Population and Family Planning (6/7), 1963-1974 (Box 4)
  - India -- Staff and Consultants Papers Re: Population and Family Planning (7/7), 1963-1974 (Box 4)
  - India -- Family Planning -- Government Programs, 1967-1969 (Box 4)
  - India -- Family Planning -- Government Publications, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
  - India -- Proposal for National Institute of Population (NIP), 1969 (Box 4)
  - India -- NIRODH -- Reports, 1968-1973 (Box 4)
  - India -- Central Family Planning Institute (CFPI) -- Sixth Annual Family Planning Communication Action Research Workshop (1968), 1967-1969 (Box 4)
  - Indonesia -- Ford Foundation Activities -- Memoranda, Reports (1/2), 1967-1979 (Box 4)
  - Indonesia -- Ford Foundation Activities -- Memoranda, Reports (2/2), 1967-1979 (Box 4)
  - Japan -- Discussion Paper and Papers of the East-West Center, 1971-1974 (Box 5)
  - Korea -- General, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Malaysia -- General File (1/2), 1964-1969 (Box 5)
  - Malaysia -- General File (2/2), 1969-1970 (Box 5)
  - Malaysia -- General Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 5)
  - Malaysia -- General Correspondence and Reports (1/2), 1969-1973 (Box 5)
  - Malaysia -- General Correspondence and Reports (2/2), 1969-1973 (Box 5)
  - Malaysia -- Conferences -- National Family Planning Seminar (June 10-12, 1968) and Related Documents, 1968-1970 (Box 5)
  - Malaysia -- "The Organization of a National Family Planning Program: Some Preliminary Considerations", 1965 (Box 5)
  - Nepal -- General Correspondence and Related Materials, 1966-1971 (Box 5)
  - Philippines -- Family Planning and Population Papers -- Memoranda, Reports, etc. (1/3), 1966-1971 (Box 5)
  - Philippines -- Family Planning and Population Papers -- Memoranda, Reports, etc. (2/3), 1966-1971 (Box 5)
  - Philippines -- Family Planning and Population Papers -- Memoranda, Reports, etc. (3/3), 1966-1971 (Box 5)
  - Philippines -- Foundation Activities, 1968-1973 (Box 5)
  - Singapore -- Foundation Activities, 1965-1973 (Box 5)
  - Taiwan -- General, 1967-1970 (Box 5)
  - Taiwan -- Taiwan Population Studies Center, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Taiwan -- Taiwan Population Studies Center -- Interim Reports, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Taiwan -- East Asia Office -- Field Reports, 1968-1975 (Box 5)
  - Taiwan -- News Letter, 1970-1977 (Box 5)
  - Thailand -- Foundation Activities, 1967-1971 (Box 5)
  - Thailand -- Correspondence Re: National Statistical Office Use of Optical Character Reader (OCR) for Population Census, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Thailand -- "Population and Family Planning in Thailand" by Gordon Perkin, et al., Oct 1968 (Box 5)
  - Europe -- France, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
  - Europe -- United Soviet Socialist Republic (USSR) -- Notes, Newspaper Articles, Reports, 1961-1975 (Box 5)
  - Western Europe -- Ford Foundation Activities, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
  - United States -- General (incl. government files), 1968-1971 (Box 6)
  - United States -- Population Growth Rate, 1972-1974 (Box 6)
  - United States -- State Department Memorandum Re: State Department Briefing, Dec 14, 1966 (Box 6)
  - United States -- Government -- President's Commission on Population and Family Planning, 1968-1972 (Box 6)
  - United States -- General -- News Clippings, 1966-1975 (Box 6)
- Conference, Meeting Files, 1967-1980; II
  Scope and Contents
  In addition to Conference Meeting files, this series also contains Program Reviews.
  - (The) American Public Health Association, 1968 (Box 6)
  - East-West Center -- Communications Institute, 1972 (Box 6)
  - East-West Center -- Conference Papers, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Economic Commission for Asia and the Far East (ECAFE) -- Conferences -- Singapore, Sep 1967 (Box 6)
  - ECAFE -- Conferences -- Bangkok, Thailand, Jun 1968 (Box 6)
  - ECAFE -- Evaluation -- Bangkok, 1969 (Box 6)
  - ECAFE -- Training -- Bangkok, 1970 (Box 6)
  - ECAFE -- Conference, Jun 19-30, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Economic and Social Commission for Asia and the Pacific (ESCAP), 1967-1975 (Box 6)
  - Congress on Optimum Population and Environment, Jun 7-11, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Bellagio III -- Conference File, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Bellagio, Italy -- Conference on the Social Sciences and Development, Feb 12-14, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Bellagio IV -- Population Conference -- Working Papers, Nov 1977 (Box 7)
  - Survey of Social Science Research Strengths Relevant to Population in the Developing World (1/3), [1971] (Box 7)
  - Survey of Social Science Research Strengths Relevant to Population in the Developing World (2/3), [1971] (Box 7)
  - Survey of Social Science Research Strengths Relevant to Population in the Developing World (3/3), [1971] (Box 7)
  - Conference on Social Science Research on Population and Development, Oct 8, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Rapporteur's Reports on Donors' Meeting, Oct 29-30, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Social Science Research on Population and Development Conferences -- Papers, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Social Science Follow-On Group -- Miscellaneous Papers, Jan 1975 (Box 7)
  - Interagency Collaboration, Feb 24-25, 1975 (Box 7)
  - International Workshop on Communication Aspects of Family Planning Programs (Bangkok, Thailand), Dec 2-14, 1968 (Box 7)
  - The International Workshop on Communications Aspects of Family Planning Programs (Bangkok, Thailand) -- Book I -- Papers, Dec 2-14, 1968 (Box 8)
  - The International Workshop on Communications Aspects of Family Planning Programs (Bangkok, Thailand) -- Book II -- Country Team Reports, Dec 2-14, 1968 (Box 8)
  - Rome Evaluation Conference (Family Planning Evaluation Conference, Rome, Italy) -- Book I, Apr 1970 (Box 8)
  - Rome Evaluation Conference (Family Planning Evaluation Conference, Rome, Italy) -- Book II, Apr 1970 (Box 8)
  - Rome Evaluation Conference (Family Planning Evaluation Conference, Rome, Italy) -- Book III, Apr 1970 (Box 8)
  - Pakistan International Family Planning Conference (Dacca, Bangladesh), Jan 1969 (Box 9)
  - Family Planning and National Development Conference (Bandung, Indonesia), Jun 1-7, 1969 (Box 9)
  - Population, Development and Applied Social Science -- Conference Report (Bangkok, Thailand), May 2-5, 1978 (Box 9)
  - Asian Population Review -- Thailand and Singapore, Oct 1972 (Box 9)
  - Asian Population Review -- Singapore Conference Notes, Nov 13-18, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Asian Population Review -- Indonesia, Nov 1972 (Box 9)
  - Asian Population Review -- Malaysia, Nov 1972 (Box 9)
  - Asian Population Review -- Pakistan, Dec 1972 (Box 9)
  - Asian Population Review -- Philippines, Dec 1972 (Box 9)
  - Asian Population Review -- Korea and Taiwan, Dec 1972-Feb 1973 (Box 9)
  - Asian Population Review -- Laos, Mar 1973 (Box 9)
  - Asian Population Review -- Bangladesh, Apr 1973 (Box 9)
  - East Africa/West Africa Regional Office Program Review, Nov 24-26, 1980 (Box 9)
- National and International Organizations, 1957-1978; III
  - International Union for the Scientific Study of Population (IUSSP), 1974-1977 (Box 10)
  - Milbank Memorial Fund -- Conference on Demographic Aspects of the Black Community, Oct 1969 (Box 10)
  - National Council on Illegitimacy (only a cross-reference sheet), undated (Box 10)
  - Organization of Demographic Associates, 1970-1972 (Box 10)
  - Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) -- Conference Materials, 1967-1977 (Box 10)
  - OECD -- Correspondence, 1967-1972 (Box 10)
  - Pan American Health Organization (PAHO)/OAS, 1967-1974 (Box 10)
  - (The) Pathfinder Fund -- Correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 10)
  - Planned Parenthood-World Population -- Jaffe's Center, 1969-1974 (Box 10)
  - Population Association of America, 1967-1972 (Box 10)
  - Population Council (1/3), 1957-1970 (Box 10)
  - Population Council (2/3), 1963-1976 (Box 11)
  - Population Council (incl. Population Institute) (3/3), 1963-1978 (Box 11)
  - Population Reference Bureau, 1967-1971 (Box 11)
  - Projects for Population Action -- Ford Foundation Employees on Advisory Board (Box 11)
  - Rand -- 1971 Annual Report (Box 11)
  - Rockefeller Foundation -- Newspaper Clippings and Press Releases, 1968-1971 (Box 11)
  - Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group of the Asia Society (SEADAG) -- Population Seminars, 1969-1973 (Box 11)
  - SIECUS, 1964-1970 (Box 11)
  - United Nations -- "Population Problems - Communications for Information and Motivation in Family Planning" (originally prepared by the Ford Foundation), Sep 1967 (Box 11)
  - United Nations Association of the United States of America, 1969-1972 (Box 11)
  - United Nations Fund for Population Activities (UNFPA) (1/2), 1971 (Box 11)
  - United Nations Fund for Population Activities (UNFPA) (2/2), 1970-1975 (Box 11)
  - World Bank, 1972-1977 (Box 12)
  - World Bank -- Correspondence, 1973 (Box 12)
  - World Education, Inc., 1970 (Box 12)
  - World Health Organization (WHO), 1975 (Box 12)
  - World Neighbors, 1966-1970 (Box 12)
  - International Development Research Center -- Ottawa, Canada -- News Releases and Ford Foundation Memoranda, 1971-1976 (Box 12)
  - International Labor Organization, 1968-1974 (Box 12)
- Subject Files, 1966-1981; IV
  - Directory of Ford Foundation Fellows in Reproductive Biology, 1960-1972, 1973 (Box 12)
  - Karen Wilhelm's Mailing -- Cover Memos -- List of Contents, 1966-1978 (Box 12)
  - Population Briefs -- Karen Wilhelm's Mailing, 1974-1977 (Box 12)
  - Population Office -- Newsletter and Mailings -- Lists, 1978-1981 (Box 12)
  - Population Office -- Newsletter and Field Office Questionnaire Responses, 1978-1980 (Box 12)
  - Population Council -- Presentation Transcript Re: Use of Red Triangle as Universal Family Planning Symbol (in English, French and Spanish) -- incl. Tape Cassette (Box 12)
  - Saunders, Lyle -- Ford Foundation Papers and Reports Re: Population and Family Planning (3/3), 1965-1970 (Box 13)
- Papers, Reports, 1965-1980; V
  - Saunders, Lyle -- Ford Foundation Papers and Reports Re: Population and Family Planning (1/3), 1965-1970 (Box 13)
  - Saunders, Lyle -- Ford Foundation Papers and Reports Re: Population and Family Planning (2/3), 1965-1970 (Box 13)
  - "Readings on Population Information and Education" -- Background Papers for Ford Foundation Meeting on Population (Elsinore, Denmark), Jun 1972 (Box 13)
  - Population Meeting (Cali, Colombia) -- Volume I, Oct 14-16, 1974 (Box 13)
  - Population Meeting (Cali, Colombia) -- Volume II, Oct 14-16, 1974 (Box 13)
  - Social Science Research on Population and Development -- Papers Presented at Conference at the Ford Foundation, Oct 29-30, 1974 (Box 13)
  - "Population, Development, and Applied Social Science: A Conference Report" by Lyle Saunders, May 2-5, 1978 (Box 13)
  - International Division Conference -- Ford Foundation -- Background Papers, Mar 21-24, 1979 (Box 13)
  - "Evaluations of the Population Council" by Ozzie Simmons, Frederick Hayes, George Zeidenstein, Dec 1979 (Box 13)
  - Community-Level Action Program Conferences -- Paper, "Community Organization and Rural Development: A Learning Process Approach" by David C. Korten, Apr 1980 (Box 13)
  - Community-Level Action Program Conferences -- Paper Re: Mexico and Central America Community-Level Action and Related Papers, 1980 (Box 13)
  - 220 -- "Ford Foundation Review Conference on the Middle East and North Africa" by William T. Irelan, [1972] (Box 13)
    Arrangement
    Numbered files
  - 221 -- Ford Foundation Memo -- "Note on Peter Schultz and Work with Videotape in Tanzania", Feb 1973 (Box 13)
  - 222 -- "The Computer-Based Education Network - A Geographically Dispersed System for Interactive Self-Paced Learning" by Daniel Alpert, Feb 1973 (Box 13)
    Arrangement note
  - 225 -- "Audio Cassette Technology" by Royal D. Colle, Oct 1973 (Box 13)
  - 226 -- Memorandum Re: Proposal for International Center for Population Communication, 1969-1974 (Box 13)
  - 227 -- "Economic Development and Labor Use" by Henry J. Bruton, Nov 1972 (Box 13)
  - 230 -- "Communications Development in Developing Countries - Who Wins, Who Loses, and Why?" by John H. Clippinger, 1976 (Box 13)
  - 248 -- "Making Research Useable" by S.E. Bunker, Jan 3, 1973 (Box 13)
  - 249 -- "Research in Family Planning Information Programs: Benchmark Surveys, Pretesting, and Evaluation" by Hans C. Groot (Box 13)
  - 266 -- Memorandum, "Mass Media and Educational Programs" by Bernard Berelson, Feb 13, 1968 (Box 13)
  - 276 -- Memorandum, "January 1975 Financial Position" by William O. Sweeney, Jan 27, 1975 (Box 13)
  - 282 -- "Strategies to Introduce Population Studies into a School System", 1976 (Box 13)
- Legal Size Documents, 1962-1979; VI
  - Alza, Michael Rees -- Patent Policy, 1970-1976 (Box 14)
  - National Workshop on Family Planning Administration, Evaluation, and Research, 1967 (Box 14)
  - India -- General Correspondence (from regional files), 1967-1969 (Box 14)
  - Kenya -- Foundation Activities (from regional files), 1968-1979 (Box 14)
  - Pakistan -- Foundation Activities -- Family Planning (from regional files), 1967 (Box 14)
  - Taiwan -- Population Studies Center -- Monthly Reports (from regional files), 1967-1975 (Box 14)
  - Thailand -- Population -- General (from regional files), 1962-1972 (Box 14)
- Appendix A: Reports, 1972
  - Saunders, Lyle and J. Gilbert Hardee; Rationale for Establishing a Population Planning Unit -- Malaysia, Aug 1972 (Report #019922)